In this video, I wanna give
在本段视频中 我想告诉大家
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
you more practical tips for getting gradient descent to work.
一些关于梯度下降算法的实用技巧
The ideas in this video will
我将集中讨论
center around the learning rate alpha.
学习率 α
Concretely, here's the gradient
具体来说 这是梯度下降算法的
descent update rule and what
更新规则
I want to do in this video
这里我想要
is tell you about what
告诉大家
I think of as debugging and some
如何调试
tips for making sure that
也就是我认为应该如何确定
Gradient Descent is working correctly
梯度下降是正常工作的
and second, I want to tell you
此外我还想告诉大家
how to choose the rates
如何选择学习率 α
out for, but this is how
也就是我平常
I go about choosing it.
如何选择这个参数
Here's something that I often do
我通常是怎样确定
to make sure gradient descent is working correctly.
梯度下降正常工作的
The job of gradient descent is
梯度下降算法所做的事情
to find a value of
就是为你找到
theta for you that, you
一个 θ 值
know, hopefully minimizes the cost function j of theta.
并希望它能够最小化代价函数 J(θ)
What I often do is therefore
我通常会在
pluck the cost function j
梯度下降算法运行时
of theta as gradient descent runs.
绘出代价函数 J(θ) 的值
So, the x-axis here is
这里的 x 轴是表示
the number of iteration of gradient
梯度下降算法的
descent and as gradient descent
迭代步数
runs, you'll hopefully get a
你可能会得到
plot that maybe looks like this.
这样一条曲线
Notice that the x-axis is
注意 这里的 x 轴
a number of iterations previously
是迭代步数
we were looking at plots of
在我们以前看到的
J of theta where the
J(θ) 曲线中
X-axis, where the horizontal axis,
x 轴 也就是横轴
was the parameter vector theta but this is not where this is.
曾经用来表示参数 θ 但这里不是
Concretely, what this point
具体来说
is is I'm going
这一点的含义是这样的
to rank gradient descent for hundred iterations.
当我运行完100步的梯度下降迭代之后
And whatever value I get
无论我得到
for theta after a hundred
什么 θ 值
of the rations and get,
总之 100步迭代之后
you know, some value of theta
我将得到
after a hundred iterations and I'm
一个 θ 值
going to evaluate the cost
根据100步迭代之后
function J of theta for
得到的这个 θ 值
the value of theta I get
我将算出
after a hundred iterations and this
代价函数 J(θ) 的值
vertical height is the
而这个点的垂直高度就代表
value of J of theta for
梯度下降算法
the value of theta I got
100步迭代之后
after a hundred other ratios of
得到的 θ
gradient descent and this
算出的 J(θ) 值
point here, that corresponds
而这个点
to the value of J of
则是梯度下降算法
theta for the theta
迭代200次之后
that I get after I've
得到的 θ
run grade and descent for two hundred iterations.
算出的 J(θ) 值
So what this plot is showing,
所以这条曲线
is it's showing the value of
显示的是
your cost function after iteration of grade and descent.
梯度下降算法迭代过程中代价函数 J(θ) 的值
And, if grade and descent is
如果梯度下降算法
working properly, then J
正常工作
of theta should decrease.
那么每一步迭代之后
after every iteration.
J(θ) 都应该下降
And one useful thing
这条曲线
that this sort of plot can
的一个用处在于
tell you also is that
它可以告诉你
if you look at the specific figure
如果你看一下
that I've drawn, it looks like
我画的这条曲线
by the time you've gotten out
当你达到
to three hundred iterations,
300步迭代之后
between three and four hundred
也就是300步到400步迭代之间
iterations, in this segment, it
也就是曲线的这一段
looks like J of theta hasn't gone down much more.
看起来 J(θ) 并没有下降多少
So by the time you get
所以当你
to four hundred iterations, it looks
到达400步迭代时
like this curve has flattened out here.
这条曲线看起来已经很平坦了
And so, way out
也就是说
here at four hundred iterations, it
在这里400步迭代的时候
looks like grade and descend has
梯度下降算法
more or less converged because your
基本上已经收敛了
cost function isn't going down much more.
因为代价函数并没有继续下降
So looking at this figure can
所以说 看这条曲线
also help you judge
可以帮助你判断
whether or not gradient descent has converged.
梯度下降算法是否已经收敛
By the way, the number of
顺便说一下
iterations that gradient descent takes
对于每一个特定的问题
to converge for a physical
梯度下降算法所需的迭代次数
application can vary a lot.
可以相差很大
So maybe for one application gradient
也许对于某一个问题
descent may converge after just
梯度下降算法
thirty iterations, for a
只需要30步迭代就可以收敛
different application gradient descent
然而换一个问题
made the 3,000 iterations.
也许梯度下降算法就需要3000步迭代
For another learning algorithm
对于另一个机器学习问题
it may take three million iterations.
则可能需要三百万步迭代
It turns out to be
实际上
very difficult to tell in
我们很难提前判断
advance how many iterations gradient
梯度下降算法
descent needs to converge, and
需要多少步迭代才能收敛
is usually by plotting this sort of plot.
通常我们需要画出这类曲线
Plotting the cause function as we increase the number of iterations.
画出代价函数随迭代步数数增加的变化曲线
It's usually by looking at these
通常 我会通过看这种曲线
plots that I tried to tell
来试着判断
if gradient descent has converged.
梯度下降算法是否已经收敛
It is also possible to come
另外 也可以
up with automatic convergence test; namely
进行一些自动的收敛测试
to have an algorithm to try
也就是说用一种算法
to tell you if gradient descent
来告诉你梯度下降算法
has converged and here's maybe
是否已经收敛
a pretty typical example of an
自动收敛测试
automatic convergence test and
一个非常典型的例子是
so, you test the clear convergence
如果代价函数 J(θ)
if your cause function jf theta
的下降小于
decreases by less than
一个很小的值 ε
some small value epsilon, some
那么就认为已经收敛
small value ten to the
比如可以选择
minus three in one iteration,
1e-3
but I find that usually
但我发现
choosing what this threshold is is pretty difficult.
通常要选择一个合适的阈值 ε 是相当困难的
So, in order to check
因此 为了检查
your gradient descent has converged, I
梯度下降算法是否收敛
actually tend to look at
我实际上还是
plots like like this
通过看
figure on the left rather than
左边的这条曲线图
rely on an automatic convergence test.
而不是依靠自动收敛测试
Looking at this sort of
此外 这种曲线图
figure can also tell you or
也可以
give you an advanced warning if maybe
在算法没有正常工作时
gradient descent is not working correctly.
提前警告你
Concretely, if you plug
具体地说
jf theta as a function
如果代价函数 J(θ)
of number of iterations, then, if
随迭代步数
you see a figure like this,
的变化曲线是这个样子
where J of theta is actually
J(θ) 实际上在不断上升
increasing, then that gives
那么这就很明确的表示
you a clear sign that gradient descent is not working.
梯度下降算法没有正常工作
And a figure like this
而这样的曲线图
usually means that you should be using a learning rate alpha.
通常意味着你应该使用较小的学习率 α
If J of theta is actually
如果 J(θ) 在上升
increasing, the most common
那么最常见的原因是
cause for that is if
你在最小化
you're trying to minimize
这样的
the function that maybe looks like this.
一个函数
That's if your learning rate is
这时如果你的学习率太大
too big then if you
当你从这里开始
start off there, gradient descent
梯度下降算法
may overshoot the minimum, send
可能将冲过最小值达到这里
you there, then if only there's
而如果你的学习率太大
too big, you may overshoot again,
你可能再次冲过最小值
it will send you there and
达到这里
so on so that what
然后一直这样下去
you really wanted was really
而你真正想要的是
start here and for to slowly go downhill.
从这里开始慢慢的下降
But if the learning is too
但是 如果学习率过大
big then gradient descent can
那么梯度下降算法
instead keep on over
将会不断的
shooting the minimum so
冲过最小值
that you actually end up
然后你将得到
getting worse and worse instead
越来越糟糕的结果
of getting the higher values of
得到越来越大的
the cost function j of theta
代价函数 J(θ) 值
so do you end up with a
所以如果你得到了
plot like and if you
这样一个曲线图
see a plot like this the
如果你看到这样一个曲线图
fix usually is to just
通常的解决方法是
use a smaller value of alpha.
使用较小的 α 值
Oh, and also of course make
当然也要确保
sure that your code does not have a bug in it.
你的代码中没有错误
But usually to watch it
但通常最可能
out of the firms is the
出现的错误是
most common, could be a common problem.
α 值过大
Similarly, sometimes, you may
同样的 有时你可能
also see j of theta
看到这种形状的
do something like this and it
J(θ) 曲线
go down for a while then
它先下降 然后上升
go up then go down for a while then go up.
接着又下降 然后又上升
Go down for a while, it
然后再次下降
goes up and so on and
再次上升 如此往复
and to fix for something like
而解决这种情况的方法
this is also to use a smaller value of algorithm.
通常同样是选择较小 α 值
I'm not going to prove it
我不打算证明这一点
here, but undeniable assumptions about
但对于我们讨论的线性回归
the cost function, which does proof of linear regression.
可以很容易从数学上证明
You can show of mathematicians have
只要学习率足够小
shown that if your learning
那么每次迭代之后
rate offer is small enough
代价函数 J(θ)
then j of theta should decrease on every single iteration.
都会下降
So, if this doesn't happen, probably
因此如果代价函数没有下降
means algorithm is too big then
那可能以为着学习率过大
you should send a smaller, but of
这时你就应该尝试一个较小的学习率
course, you all So you don't
当然 你也不希望
want your learning rate to be
学习度太小
too small because if you
因为如果这样
do that, if you were
如果你这么做
to do that, then gradient descent can be slow to converge.
那么梯度下降算法可能收敛得很慢
And if alpha were too
如果学习率 α 太小
small, you might end up
你可能
starting out here, say, and,
从这里开始
you know, end up taking just
然后很缓慢很缓慢
minuscule, minuscule baby steps.
向最低点移动
Right?
这样一来
And just taking a lot
你需要迭代很多次
of iterations before you finally get to the minimum.
才能到达最低点
And so, if alpha is too
因此 如果学习率 α 太小
small, gradient descent can
梯度下降算法
make very slow progress and be slow to converge.
的收敛将会很缓慢
To summarize, if the learning
总结一下
rate is too small, you can
如果学习率 α 太小
have a slow convergence problem, and
你会遇到收敛速度慢的问题
if the learning rate is too
而如果学习率 α 太大
large, j of theta may
代价函数 J(θ) 可能不会在
not decrease on every iteration
每次迭代都下降
and may not even converge.
甚至可能不收敛
In some cases, if the learning
在某些情况下
rate is too large, slow convergence
如果学习率 α 过大
is also possible, but the
也可能出现收敛缓慢的问题
more common problem you see
但更常见的情况是
is that just that j of
你会发现代价函数 J(θ)
theta may not decrease on every iteration.
并不会在每次迭代之后都下降
And in order to debug all
而为了调试
of these things, often plotting that
所有这些情况
j of theta as a function
绘制J(θ)随迭代步数变化的曲线
of the number of iterations can help you figure out what's going on.
通常可以帮助你弄清楚到底发生了什么
Concretely, what I actually
具体来说
do when I run gradient
当我运行梯度下降算法时
descent is I would try a range of values.
我通常会尝试一系列α值
So just try running gradient descent
所以在运行梯度下降算法制
with a range of values for
请尝试不同的 α 值
alpha, like 0.001, 0.01,
比如0.001, 0.01
so these are a
这里每隔10倍
factor of 10 differences, and
取一个值
for these differences of this
然后对于这些不同的 α 值
of alpha, just plot j of
绘制 J(θ)
theta as a function of number
随迭代步数变化的曲线
of iterations and then pick
然后选择
the value of alpha that, you
看上去使得 J(θ)
know, seems to be causing j of theta to decrease rapidly.
快速下降的一个 α 值
In fact, what I do actually isn't these steps of ten.
事实上 我通常并不是隔10倍取一个值
So, you know, this is
你可以看到
a scale factor of ten if you reach the top.
这里是每隔10倍取一个值
What I'll actually do is try
我通常取的
this range of values and
是这些 α 值
so on where this is,
一直这样下去
you know, opening 001
你看 先取0.001
then increase the linear rate to
然后将学习率增加3倍
3.4 to get 0.03 and then
得到0.003
to step up this is another
然后这一步
roughly 3 fold increase point
从0.003到0.01
of 0.03 to 0.01s and so these
又大约增加了3倍
are roughly, you know,
所以 在为梯度下降算法
trying out gradient descents with each
选择合适的学习率时
value I try being about
我大致是
3X bigger than the previous value.
按3的倍数来取值的
So what I'll do is a range
所以我会尝试一系列α值
of values until I've made sure
直到我找到
that I've found one value that
一个值
is too small and made sure
它不能再小了
I found one value that is
同时找到另一个值
too large, and then I sort
它不能再大了
of try to pick the largest
然后我尽量挑选
possible value or just something
其中最大的那个 α 值
slightly smaller than the
或者一个比最大值
largest reasonable value that I found.
略小一些的合理的值
And when I do that
而当我做了以上工作时
usually it just gives me
我通常就可以得到
a good learning rate for my problem.
一个不错的学习率
And if you do this
如果也你这样做
too, hopefully you will be
那么你也能够
able to choose a good
为你的梯度下降算法
learning rate for your implementation
找到一个合适的
of gradient descent.
学习率值